Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and you've probably heard us talking a little bit about small talk the
我是Catherine，你可能已经听到我们过去几周聊了一些关于闲聊的话题。
past few weeks.
过去几周。
We have another episode about small talk and we're going to teach you some things that
我们还有一集关于闲聊的内容，会教你在遇到很久没见或甚至初次见面的人时可以说些什么。
you can say to people when you haven't seen them or maybe even met them before.
你可以在遇到很久没见或甚至初次见面的人时使用。
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to talk to a stranger.
今天我们要和一个陌生人聊天。
So we're going to talk very briefly about some casual topic.
所以我们会简短地聊一些随意的话题。
And so let's jump into the dialogue and see what happens.
那我们就直接进入对话，看看会发生什么。
Excuse me, is this seat taken?
打扰一下，这个座位有人吗？
No, please feel free.
没有，请随意。
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢。
Do you work in Shanghai?
你在上海工作吗？
Yes, I do.
是的，我在上海工作。
How about you?
你呢？
No, I'm a tourist.
不，我是游客。
This place is amazing.
这个地方太棒了。
It's much bigger than I imagined and much more exciting.
它比我想象的大得多，也精彩得多。
There's so much to see here.
这里有很多值得看的东西。
You can say that again.
你说得没错。
It's much more modern than people imagine.
它比人们想象的现代化得多。
Where are you from?
你从哪里来？
Well, let's see.
嗯，让我想想。
I'm from Kansas originally, a much quieter and more peaceful place than here.
我原本来自堪萨斯，一个比这里安静和平得多的地方。
That's for sure.
确实如此。
But I'm living in Paris right now.
但我现在住在巴黎。
Oh, Paris.
哦，巴黎。
Wonderful.
太棒了。
I'd love to visit sometime.
我以后很想去看看。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now we're going to take a look at a lot of phrases on this occasion.
现在我们要看看这次对话中的很多短语。
So let's go for fluency builder part one.
那我们进入流利度构建第一部分。
Fluency builder.
流利度构建。
All right.
好的。
So the first phrase we have is a very common phrase if you're in a train or on a bus.
第一个短语非常常见，如果你在火车或公交车上。
You hear the phrase, is this seat taken?
你会听到这个短语：这个座位有人吗？
Right.
对。
So Michelle came up to the stranger and said, excuse me, is this seat taken?
所以Michelle走向陌生人说：打扰一下，这个座位有人吗？
That means, is anybody sitting here?
意思是：这里有人坐吗？
It basically means, can I sit here?
基本上就是问：我能坐这儿吗？
Right.
对。
This is a very polite way of asking if you can sit down in the seat.
这是一种非常礼貌的问法，询问是否可以坐下。
You can also say it in a restaurant, at a movie theater, in a classroom.
你可以在餐厅、电影院、教室里这么说。
So remember this one.
所以记住这个。
This was a really, really common phrase.
这是一个非常非常常见的短语。
So it's a very polite way of saying, can I sit down?
所以这是一种非常礼貌的说法，意思是：我能坐下吗？
That's right.
没错。
You're asking for permission basically.
你基本上是在请求许可。
Is the seat taken?
这个座位有人吗？
Because what if a person says, well, no, it's not.
因为如果对方说：嗯，没有。
Do you have to say, may I sit down?
你是不是要说：我可以坐下吗？
May I take a seat?
我可以坐吗？
Well, if they say, I'm sorry, someone is sitting here.
嗯，如果他们说：抱歉，有人坐这儿。
That means that maybe they're waiting for a friend and then no, you can't sit there.
那意味着他们可能在等朋友，所以你不能坐那儿。
But if they say, sure, like in the dialogue, feel free, then you're really basically able
但如果他们说：当然，就像对话里的“请随意”，那你基本上就可以坐下了。
to sit down.
坐下。
No problem.
没问题。
Right.
对。
So the stranger answers by saying, no, please feel free.
所以陌生人回答说：没有，请随意。
So he says, no, the seat is not taken.
所以他说：没有，座位没人。
Please feel free.
请随意。
What does he mean by this?
他这是什么意思？
Okay.
好的。
Feel free is a very unusual phrase in English, but one that you're going to hear a lot.
“Feel free”在英语中是一个不寻常的短语，但你会经常听到。
It basically means do what you want to do.
它基本上意思是：做你想做的事。
Okay.
好的。
So if I want to sit down, I say, is this seat taken?
所以如果我想坐下，我会说：这个座位有人吗？
If you say, feel free, Marco, that means feel free to sit down.
如果你说：随意，Marco，那就意味着随意坐下。
Okay.
好的。
So we can complete the sentence by saying, no, please feel free to sit down.
所以我们可以把句子补充完整：没有，请随意坐下。
But it's kind of stating the obvious.
但这有点显而易见。
You're saying basically feel free to do what you want.
你基本上是在说：随意做你想做的事。
That's right.
没错。
But you could use it in other ways.
但你也可以在其他场合使用它。
For example, Hey Marco, are you using this pen right here?
比如：嘿，Marco，你正在用这支笔吗？
No, no, feel free.
没有，没有，随意用。
That means feel free to use my pen.
意思是随意用我的笔。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
非常好。
And so then they started talking about what they do, where they work.
然后他们开始聊各自做什么工作、在哪里工作。
And Michelle said, yes, I work in Shanghai.
米歇尔说，是的，我在上海工作。
How about you?
你呢？
Oh, how about you?
哦，你呢？
Now this is a really important construction.
这是一个非常重要的结构。
This is a really important phrase in English.
这是英语中一个非常重要的短语。
And I think a lot of people make mistakes with this.
我觉得很多人会在这里犯错。
So how about you means, do you work in Shanghai?
所以“how about you”的意思是，你在上海工作吗？
I just said I work in Shanghai, but how about you?
我刚说了我在上海工作，但你呢？
Do you?
你呢？
Right.
对。
Exactly.
没错。
So that's saying, and you, do you work here?
所以这相当于说，那你呢，你在这里工作吗？
Or and you, what do you do?
或者，那你呢，你是做什么的？
How about you?
你呢？
Now, the common mistake with how about you or using the construction how about is that
关于“how about you”或使用“how about”这个结构，常见的错误是
for some reason, some people seem to think that it means how is it?
不知为何，有些人似乎认为它意思是“怎么样？”
So for example, if someone says, how about your weekend?
比如，如果有人说“how about your weekend？”
That's wrong.
那是错的。
No, we don't say that.
不，我们不这么说。
How was your weekend?
应该说“how was your weekend？”
But in this case, how about you always follows a statement.
但在这种情况下，“how about you”总是跟在陈述句后面。
Okay.
好的。
So yes, I do live in Shanghai.
所以，是的，我确实住在上海。
How about you?
你呢？
That means, do you live in Shanghai?
这意思是，你住在上海吗？
Right.
对。
If I say, I would like to eat a hamburger and French fries.
如果我说，我想吃一个汉堡和薯条。
How about you?
你呢？
What would you like to eat?
你想吃什么？
Exactly.
没错。
So remember, that's the way that you use how about.
所以记住，这就是你使用“how about”的方式。
Never say how about your weekend or how about your vacation when you want to ask, how was
永远不要说“how about your weekend”或“how about your vacation”当你想问“怎么样”时，
it?
怎么样？
Don't say that.
别那么说。
No, basically, this is a way to reply to someone when they're telling you about their experience.
不，基本上，这是一种回应别人的方式，当他们告诉你他们的经历时。
You want to talk about yours.
你想谈谈你的经历。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, so let's take a break.
好的，那我们休息一下。
Let's review everything and we'll be back with Fluency Builder part two.
我们来回顾一下所有内容，然后回来继续流畅表达第二部分。
Excuse me, is this seat taken?
打扰一下，这个座位有人吗？
No, please feel free.
没有，请随意。
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢。
Do you work in Shanghai?
你在上海工作吗？
Yes, I do.
是的，我在上海工作。
How about you?
你呢？
No, I'm a tourist.
不，我是游客。
This place is amazing.
这个地方太棒了。
It's much bigger than I imagined and much more exciting.
它比我想象的大得多，也刺激得多。
There's so much to see here.
这里有很多可看的东西。
You can say that again.
你说得太对了。
It's much more modern than people imagine.
它比人们想象的现代化得多。
Where are you from?
你从哪里来？
Well, let's see.
嗯，让我想想。
I'm from Kansas originally, a much quieter and more peaceful place than here.
我原本来自堪萨斯州，那里比这里安静平和得多。
That's for sure.
确实如此。
Uh-huh.
嗯哼。
But I'm living in Paris right now.
但我现在住在巴黎。
Oh, Paris.
哦，巴黎。
That's wonderful.
那太棒了。
I'd love to visit sometime.
我希望能找个时间去参观。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's continue with some more phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在让我们继续学习流畅表达中的更多短语。
Okay, this first phrase is one that I really like to use.
好的，第一个短语是我非常喜欢用的。
The phrase is from Michelle.
这个短语来自米歇尔。
She says, you can say that again.
她说，你说得太对了。
But she's talking about how Shanghai is so big and so exciting.
但她是在说上海有多大、多刺激。
And Michelle says, you can say that again.
然后米歇尔说，你说得太对了。
Now, what does this mean, Marco?
马可，这是什么意思？
That's right.
没错。
So she is basically agreeing with the person.
所以她基本上是在同意对方的话。
The stranger says, Shanghai is amazing.
那个陌生人说，上海太棒了。
It's great.
它很棒。
There's so much to see.
有很多可看的东西。
Michelle says, you can say that again.
米歇尔说，你说得太对了。
It's saying, I agree with you.
这表示，我同意你。
You are so right.
你说得太对了。
I really agree.
我真的很同意。
All right, so this is very emphatic.
好的，所以这个表达非常强调。
That means that it's really, it's more than just I agree.
这意味着它真的，不仅仅是“我同意”。
I really, really agree.
我真的、真的同意。
The person really feels something about this, feels passionately about it.
这个人对此事有强烈的感受，充满热情。
That's right.
没错。
So if you go to the movies and you say, oh, that movie was terrible, you can say.
所以如果你去看电影，你说，哦，那部电影太糟糕了，你可以说。
You can say that again.
你说得对极了。
Exactly.
正是。
It means, oh, I agree.
它的意思是，哦，我同意。
It was really bad.
它真的很差。
That's right.
没错。
Now, when Michelle asked the stranger where he was from, he says, I'm from Kansas originally.
现在，当米歇尔问那个陌生人他是哪里人时，他说，我原本来自堪萨斯州。
Okay, what's originally?
好的，“originally”是什么意思？
I'm original?
我是原创的？
No.
不。
I'm from Kansas originally means maybe I don't live in Kansas now, but that's where I come
“我原本来自堪萨斯州”可能意味着我现在不住在堪萨斯州，但那是我来的地方。
from.
来自。
Origin, originally.
起源，原本。
That means, you know, at the beginning.
这意味着，你知道，一开始。
Right.
对。
And remember, Kansas, by the way, is one of the states in the United States.
记住，顺便说一下，堪萨斯州是美国的一个州。
And so he's saying he's from Kansas, but now he lives in Paris.
所以他说他来自堪萨斯州，但现在他住在巴黎。
So that's why you say, I'm originally from Kansas, but I live in Paris.
所以这就是为什么你说，我原本来自堪萨斯州，但我住在巴黎。
All right, so Marco, you live here in Shanghai, but where do you come from originally?
好的，马可，你住在上海，但你原本来自哪里？
Originally, I'm from Ecuador.
原本，我来自厄瓜多尔。
All right.
好的。
And I'm originally from Chicago, but I currently live in China.
我原本来自芝加哥，但我目前住在中国。
That's right.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
And as he was talking about Kansas, he also said that, well, it's obviously a lot quieter
当他谈论堪萨斯州时，他还说，嗯，那里显然安静得多。
and more peaceful.
也更平和。
And then he ends his statement by saying, that's for sure.
然后他结束陈述时说，“那是肯定的”。
That's for sure.
那是肯定的。
And this is a phrase that we use to add emphasis on something.
这是一个我们用来强调某事的短语。
It's almost like saying, this is a really quiet, much quieter and peaceful place.
这几乎就像在说，这真是一个安静得多、平和得多的地方。
That's for sure.
那是肯定的。
It really is.
确实如此。
It's not like you're adding anything to the statement, like no meaning, but you're actually
并不是你在陈述中加了什么，比如没有新意思，但你实际上。
kind of making it more strong.
让它更有力了。
Right.
对。
You're saying it's a fact.
你在说这是一个事实。
It's a fact.
这是一个事实。
It's really this way.
它真的是这样。
So obviously, Kansas compared to Shanghai is a lot more quieter.
所以显然，堪萨斯州与上海相比安静得多。
That's for sure.
那是肯定的。
Mm-hmm.
嗯哼。
Or I could say that in Chicago in the winter, it's a lot colder than Shanghai.
或者我可以说，在芝加哥的冬天，比上海冷得多。
That's for sure.
那是肯定的。
Right.
对。
So again, you're emphasizing on your statement, telling everyone that it's very, very much
所以再次，你在强调你的陈述，告诉每个人它非常、非常。
like this.
像这样。
That's how it really is.
它真的是这样。
Okay.
好的。
So that's all the phrases we have for you.
所以这就是我们为你准备的所有短语。
Why don't we listen to our dialogue one last time.
我们最后再听一遍对话吧。
Excuse me.
打扰一下。
Is this seat taken?
这个座位有人吗？
No, please feel free.
没有，请随意。
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢。
Do you work in Shanghai?
你在上海工作吗？
Yes, I do.
是的，我工作。
How about you?
你呢？
No, I'm a tourist.
不，我是游客。
This place is amazing.
这个地方太棒了。
It's much bigger than I imagined and much more exciting.
它比我想象的大得多，也刺激得多。
There's so much to see here.
这里有很多可看的东西。
You can say that again.
你说得对极了。
It's much more modern than people imagine.
它比人们想象的现代得多。
Where are you from?
你从哪里来？
Well, let's see.
嗯，让我想想。
I'm from Kansas originally, a much quieter and more peaceful place than here.
我原本来自堪萨斯州，一个比这里安静得多、平和得多的地方。
That's for sure.
那是肯定的。
Uh-huh.
嗯哼。
But I'm living in Paris right now.
但我现在住在巴黎。
Oh, Paris.
哦，巴黎。
Wonderful.
太棒了。
I'd love to visit sometime.
我希望有一天能去参观。
All right.
好的。
So small talk with a stranger.
所以和陌生人闲聊。
This is actually a very common scenario.
这实际上是一个非常常见的场景。
If in a bus, in a train, you sit next to a stranger, this is more or less what you're
如果你在公交车或火车上坐在一个陌生人旁边，这差不多就是你们会聊的话题。
going to talk about.
要聊的内容。
Where are you from?
你从哪里来？
What do you do?
你是做什么的？
Where do you live?
你住在哪里？
That's right.
没错。
And you don't even have to talk about this with a total stranger.
而且你甚至不需要和完全陌生的人聊这些。
You could actually use this with someone that you're working with or just an acquaintance.
你其实可以用这些话题和同事或熟人聊。
So basically, these are key questions that you would ask someone that you don't really
所以基本上，这些是你问不太熟悉的人时会问的关键问题。
know very well.
不太了解的人。
That's right.
没错。
And as you can see, you're not really going into any deep personal questions.
而且你看，你并没有深入问任何私人问题。
It's very light conversation, very brief as well.
这是很轻松的对话，也很简短。
That's right.
没错。
And I would like to add that in American culture, people often think it's very rude to ask someone
我想补充一点，在美国文化中，人们通常认为问别人赚多少钱、公寓多少钱、车多少钱是非常粗鲁的。
how much do you earn, how much is your apartment, how much is your car.
所以在美国文化中的闲聊里，我认为在很多西方文化中，我们不会谈论金钱或宗教。
So in small talk in American culture, and I think a lot of Western cultures, we don't
talk about money or religion.
所以在美国文化中的闲聊里，我认为在很多西方文化中，我们不会谈论金钱或宗教。
So what religion are you?
那你信什么教？
So I think it's important to talk about things that are very simple.
所以我认为聊一些非常简单的事情很重要。
What do you do for a living?
你是做什么工作的？
Where do you live?
你住在哪里？
How's the weather?
天气怎么样？
These things.
这些话题。
Yes.
是的。
This is exactly, I think, one of the main points that when you're learning a language
我认为这恰恰是学习英语这类语言时的一个重点，不仅要理解语言，还要理解文化。
such as English, not only to understand the language, but also the culture.
这非常非常不同，尤其是在亚洲文化中，比如你去理发店，理发师问你赚多少钱，这没什么大不了的。
It's very, very different, especially, for example, in Asian cultures where it's no big
deal if you go to the hairdresser and the hairdresser asks you how much you earn.
这非常非常不同，尤其是在亚洲文化中，比如你去理发店，理发师问你赚多少钱，这没什么大不了的。
But in the United States or many Western countries, it's not something that you talk about your
但在美国或许多西方国家，谈论薪水或直接问这种事是不合适的。
salary or that you really ask.
It's kind of personal information.
这算是私人信息。
It is.
是的。
And if you talk about it, you might make people very uncomfortable.
如果你聊这些，可能会让人很不舒服。
And so I recommend talking about some of the things that we've discussed here and some
所以我建议聊一些我们在这里讨论过的话题，以及本系列其他关于闲聊的课程中讨论过的话题。
of the things that we've discussed in other lessons in this series about small talk.
That's right.
没错。
And if you have any questions or any comments about this lesson, you can come and visit
如果你对本课有任何问题或评论，可以来访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com。
us at EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you guys there.
我们期待在那里见到你们。
Until next time.
下次再见。
Bye.
再见。